<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Meta on Jan Kremer</title>
    <link>https://jankremer.eu/tags/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meta on Jan Kremer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>de</language>
    <lastBuildDate>2023-12-30 08:34</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jankremer.eu/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m currently doing</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/now/</link>
      <pubDate>2023-12-30 08:34</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning&#34;&gt;Learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pharmazeutische Technologie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kaffee und Zigaretten – Ferdinand von Schirach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;watching&#34;&gt;Watching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Germany&amp;rsquo;s next topmodel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rosins Restaurants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Batman – The animated series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Band of Brothers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening&#34;&gt;Listening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kölsche Karnevalsmusik (yeah I know Karneval is over)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I use</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/uses/</link>
      <pubDate>2023-12-30 08:03</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/uses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MacBook Pro 2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iPhone X&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Watch SE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPods Pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logitech MX Master 3 (rarely)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;software&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Software&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unless otherwise stated&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Apple default apps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RSS reader&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Notes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;To-Do list&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://culturedcode.com/things&#34;&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Text editor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://neovim.io&#34;&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://helix-editor.com&#34;&gt;Helix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Word processing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://typst.app&#34;&gt;Typst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Window manager&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ianyh/Amethyst&#34;&gt;Amethyst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Terminal emulator&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty&#34;&gt;Kitty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Package manager&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nixos.org&#34;&gt;Nix&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://brew.sh&#34;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploy a website using Git</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/blog/git-deploy/</link>
      <pubDate>2023-09-25 00:00</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/blog/git-deploy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;git-ftp&#34;&gt;Git-ftp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tested a lot of different FTP programs including GUIs, TUIs and CLIs.
There might be a problem with the FTP server but I don&amp;rsquo;t control that unfortunately.
The only program working flawlessly so far is &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-ftp.github.io/&#34;&gt;git-ftp&lt;/a&gt;, a plugin for Git.
Not only is this perfectly integrated into git, which I am using anyway.
Also no errors occurred so far.
Plus I can automate the upload using &lt;a href=&#34;#git-hooks&#34;&gt;hooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;git-hooks&#34;&gt;Git hooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real MVP however is &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/githooks&#34;&gt;Git Hooks&lt;/a&gt;.
Hooks are scripts that run automatically on certain Git events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did, for example, create a hook to automacally build the website after commiting a change.
Yes, this could introduce problems such as breaking changes and I end up with a broken website, but as I test it regularly this should not become a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second hook I created pushes the website to the FTP server whenever I push to the remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;git-submodule&#34;&gt;Git submodule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently discovered that I can use &lt;code&gt;git submodule&lt;/code&gt; to add the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; folder created by Hugo.
This allows me to upload the repository to my pages repository on Codeberg and have the site mirrored there.
Secoundly, it allows me to upload the website with git-ftp without uploading everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What awesome features of Git are you using?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RSS</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/blog/rss/</link>
      <pubDate>2023-09-01 00:00</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/blog/rss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-rss&#34;&gt;What is RSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, RSS stood for &amp;ldquo;RDF/Rich Site Summary&amp;rdquo; but was later changed to &amp;ldquo;Really Simple Syndication&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSS is a way to subscribe to a website.
Whenever that website updates it writes its changes to a &lt;code&gt;XML&lt;/code&gt; file.
You can then read this XML file and see what changed at a glance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many websites use RSS including YouTube, &lt;del&gt;Reddit&lt;/del&gt; Lemmy, &lt;del&gt;Twitter&lt;/del&gt; Mastodon, most news sites, and almost any blog out there.
For many blogs, RSS is the main way to distribute new posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSS is experiencing a Renaissance at the moment:
Many people are now seeing the damages done by algorithmic feeds and want to go back to purely chronological feeds.
RSS provides a perfect infrastructure for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-read-rss&#34;&gt;How to read RSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need a feed reader. On macOS and iOS I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/a&gt;.
For terminal fans &lt;a href=&#34;https://newsboat.org&#34;&gt;Newsboat&lt;/a&gt; is the way to go.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thunderbird.net/&#34;&gt;Thunderbird&lt;/a&gt; is also a good choice but there are tons of programs that can read RSS feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s bascially it. Now you need to add some feeds and you are ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend picking a reader that can also fetch the article without opening the browser and loading a ton of ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pro tip: You can export your subscibtions to a &lt;code&gt;OPML&lt;/code&gt; file and import them into any RSS reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-distribute-rss&#34;&gt;How to distribute RSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the hardest question to answer about RSS as there are endless possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way would probably be to use a service such as Mastodon that generates the feed automatically.
If that platform isn&amp;rsquo;t for you, WordPress is a good way to host a blog.
I read about people setting up their own scripts that automatically update the feed for new posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; which is a &lt;em&gt;static site generator&lt;/em&gt;.
It generates feeds automatically but lies somewhere between WordPress and writing your own scripts in terms of how tech savvy you should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-find-rss&#34;&gt;How to find RSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to a website you like, copy the URL and paste it into your RSS reader.
Modern feed readers can find RSS feed on their own, you just have to provide a link to the site you want to subscribe to.
If that is not the case, you could try adding &lt;code&gt;/index.xml&lt;/code&gt; to the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some sites, like this one, also link to their RSS feeds.
Often those links are a the bottom of the website and are either marked as &lt;code&gt;RSS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Feed&lt;/code&gt;, or just use the RSS logo.
I additionally provide links to my subprojects such as my &lt;a href=&#34;https://jankremer.eu/micro&#34;&gt;microblog&lt;/a&gt; or my &lt;a href=&#34;https://jankremer.eu/fotos&#34;&gt;photos&lt;/a&gt;.
Feel free to add them to your reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think RSS is on the rise.
It&amp;rsquo;s an old protocol that survived numerous challenges
It provides an escape from the algorithms and large social media companies.
It also provides a way for content creators to distribute their content on their own without any middleman.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 cent blog</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/blog/hosting/</link>
      <pubDate>2023-08-27 00:00</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/blog/hosting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, the title is correct.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://knowyourmeme.com/photos/1191035&#34;&gt;Well, actually&lt;/a&gt; it is 0.119 € per
month or 14.28 € for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, it was a special offer and only covers the domain.
Fortunately, my provider, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netim.com/en&#34;&gt;Netim&lt;/a&gt; has a free hosting plan with fits my needs.
I even get email hosting with my own domain.
There are also services like &lt;a href=&#34;https://neocities.org&#34;&gt;Neocities&lt;/a&gt; where you can host your website for free if you are willing to live with a subdomain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-should-i-xyz-is-free&#34;&gt;Why should I? XYZ is free!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can post wherever you want.
𝕏 (formerly known as Twitter) is free&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Mastodon is free, Facebook, Instagram, Threads, Reddit, you name them, are all free, but you are giving up your freedoms.
Mastodon might be a little better than the rest, but ultimately you depend on the host to let you post there.
And they can block you and delete all your data without even giving you any notice.
I hope you have a backup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hosting this blog allows me to write whatever I want.
Sure, Netim could also block me and delete my data, but since I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; I always have everything backed up on my system anyways.
In a matter of hours I could be up and running on another hosting provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can also use any format I want and have nearly endless possibilities to customize my blog.
The sky is the limit.
For example am I hosting my own &lt;a href=&#34;https://jankremer.eu/fotos&#34;&gt;photos&lt;/a&gt; instead of using Instagram and my own &lt;a href=&#34;https://jankremer.eu/micro&#34;&gt;microblog&lt;/a&gt; instead of using Twitter/Mastodon.
Whatever media I plan to share in the future, there is a solution out there.
Want comments? I&amp;rsquo;m trying &lt;a href=&#34;https://cactus.chat&#34;&gt;Cactus Comments&lt;/a&gt; at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or is it? I&amp;rsquo;m not in the loop.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genesis</title>
      <link>https://jankremer.eu/blog/genesis/</link>
      <pubDate>2022-12-10 00:00</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jankremer.eu/blog/genesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Als ich vor ca. einem Jahr diese Domain kaufte, wusste ich noch nicht was ich damit anstellen will. Ich wusste nur: &lt;strong&gt;Ich will endlich eine eigene Webseite haben.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In meinen ersten Stunden Informatik in der Schule (vor über 10 Jahren) lernten wir die Grundlagen des Webdesigns mit &lt;em&gt;HTML&lt;/em&gt; und &lt;em&gt;CSS&lt;/em&gt;, und da ich zunächst nicht viel Zeit hatte erstellte ich genau mit diesen Tools eine kleine Startseite. Mehr schlecht als recht aber immerhin hatte ich etwas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im März diesen Jahres hatte ich dann ein wenig Zeit mich genauer mit dem Thema zu beschäftigen und fand dabei den sogenannten &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamstack.org&#34;&gt;Jamstack&lt;/a&gt;. Jamstack sind Tools zur schnellen und einfachen Aufstellen von Webseite. Dies können große Projekte sein oder wie in meinem Fall ein kleiner Blog. Zuerst probierte ich &lt;a href=&#34;https://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; was mir jedoch nicht so gut taugte und stieß dann auf &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. Mit einer Vielzahl an modernen Designs und einer klinderleichten Handhaben konnte ich schnell überzeugt werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heute weiß ich zwar immer noch nicht, was ich hiermit in Zukunft machen werde, aber ich denke es ist wichtiger den je ein Sprachrohr zu haben, das unabhängig ist von der Willkür großer Plattformen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bis bald und viel Spaß!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S.: Dieses wunderschöne &lt;em&gt;Theme&lt;/em&gt;, das ich hier benutze, heißt &lt;a href=&#34;https://git.io/hugo-congo&#34;&gt;Congo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
